All right, so let's talk about how the
United States used trade policies and
the Monroe Doctrine and other events
like the War of 1812 to do its very best
to get its big boy world power pants on
in the early 19th century. So, if you're
ready to get them brain cows milked,
let's get to it. Okay, so in 1809, James
Madison became president and a chief
goal of his was to strengthen the United
States in the eyes of the world as a
respectable world power. I mean, yes,
the Treaty of Paris in 1783 formally
established the independence of the
United States, but great European powers
didn't take the new nation as seriously
as the Americans took themselves. It was
kind of like when you were a kid and you
dressed up as a superhero and you felt
real awesome and you were sure that your
mom would respect your obvious crime
fighting abilities. But then she looked
at you and said, "Oh, you're so cute,
but go finish folding my laundry." And
that's kind of how the great European
powers saw the United States. Case in
point, after the Revolutionary War,
Britain kept occupying forces in their
western force, and the Spanish sold
weapons to American Indians and
encouraged them to attack American
migrants heading west. Clearly, there
was a lack of respect for the new nation
in a baggy superhero costume. But not to
worry, the US attempted to enact several
policies during this period to claim its
spot on the stage of world powers. Oh,
and by the way, if you want note guys to
follow along with this video and all my
videos, then check that link in the
description. Okay, so the first way the
US tried to claim its spot on the world
stage was by promoting foreign trade.
Now, recall from a previous video that
one way European powers did not take the
United States seriously was to ignore
the position of US neutrality during the
Napoleonic Wars. For example, British
ships continued to impress or forcibly
conscript American sailors, and the
French seized American merchant ships as
if they were enemies in the war. So, to
combat this, Thomas Jefferson led
Congress to pass the Embargo Act, which
cut off all US trade with foreign powers
in hopes of forcing them to accept US
neutrality. And to put it mildly, this
law did not have the intended effect.
Mainly the result of the embargo act was
that the people in the US suffered
economically on account of the sharp
decline of international trade. Okay, so
that didn't work. But just before James
Madison took office, Congress passed the
non-intercourse act in 1809 which
replaced the embargo act. And basically
instead of cutting off all foreign
trade, the non-intercourse act cut off
trade with Great Britain and France
only. And you know, opening the
international economy helped somewhat,
but it didn't have any dramatic effects
and is generally considered a failure to
address the nation's economic woes. And
by my account, that's strike two on
making European powers take us
seriously. So, what else we got? Well, a
year later in 1810, Congress passed
Mak's bill number two in order to
stimulate the economy. And look, I'm not
saying that I could do any better, but
in hindsight, this was a pretty moronic
piece of legislation, and I'm about to
tell you why. First, the bill
temporarily opened US trade to Britain
and France on the condition that their
exported goods arrived to the US on
Americans ship. Second, the bill
introduced a kind of international
blackmail. Like remember that the whole
problem was that neither Britain nor
France were respecting US neutrality. So
the bill said that if either country
respected US neutrality then the US
would embargo the other country. In
other words, if France agreed to respect
US neutrality and stop seizing ships and
cargo, then the US would close off trade
with Great Britain or vice versa. So
while the goal of this legislation was
to increase the stature of the United
States in the eyes of European powers,
it actually did the opposite. Like the
leader of France, Napoleon Bonapart,
heard this and was like, "It's like
they're begging me to take advantage of
them." And that's exactly what he did.
He sent a letter to Madison agreeing to
respect US neutrality. And so the US cut
off trade with Great Britain, which hurt
them economically while they were trying
to wage war against France. And to be
clear, Madison was pretty suspicious of
Napoleon's motives, but in the end, he
really didn't have a choice. So, not
only did that move increase tensions
between Great Britain and the US, but
Napoleon used the US for his own gain
since he never intended to honor
American neutrality in the first place.
And in the end, this series of laws only
proved that when it came to global
affairs, the US was in fact not a big
boy, but very much a small boy. Okay, so
maybe the US can gain some respect on
the world stage by claiming territory
here in North America. So, let's see how
that goes. And just to be clear, a big
part of this desire to expand was the US
desire to bring the Indian policy under
federal control and therefore open
American Indian lands to US expansion.
Now, after US troops defeated an
American Indian alliance at the Battle
of Fallen Timbers in 1794, American
Indians in the Ohio River Valley created
a new alliance to resist American
migration into their lands. And the
alliance was led by a Shaunie prophet
named Tenqatawa and his warrior brother
Tcuma. They instructed their followers
to give up all aspects of white culture
and fight to establish their right to
remain in their ancestral land. And if
they did so, the great spirit would
protect them and facilitate their
success. And if your little neurons are
twitching right now because that sounds
a lot like the Pueblo revolt from unit
one, then give your brain a high five.
Anyway, as the movement gathered more
followers, they established their base
in modern-day Indiana, a settlement
known as Profit Town, situated along the
Typicanw River in 1808. And then later,
the territorial governor of Indiana,
William Henry Harrison, met with several
tribal leaders, got them drunk, and
persuaded them to sell the US millions
of acres for a fraction of its worth.
Now, that sounds like a dirty move.
Well, then Tecumpsa would agree with
you. When he heard about it, Tecumpsa
was enraged, not only because of the
trickery, but because American Indians
did not believe that land could be
bought and sold like a commodity since
it belonged to all of them communally.
Therefore, Tecumpsa intensified his
efforts to recruit other American Indian
groups to their resistance movement. And
while he was away in the south
recruiting more people to his movement,
Harrison apparently thought it was time
for yet another dirty move. He sent
troops to attack Profit Town. And with
their main warrior gone, the US secured
an easy victory. So in the aftermath,
Tecumpsa and many of his followers
retreated to Canada where they allied
with the British and would eventually
fight against the Americans in the War
of 1812. Now, there were certainly more
territorial gains during this period,
but I'll tell you about them in a
moment. But for now, we need to focus on
how the US actually did gain some
respect on the world stage, and that
happened as the result of the War of
1812, which was followed up by the
Monroe Doctrine. So, let's talk about
each. Now, the War of 1812 was another
conflict between the United States and
Great Britain. And some historians even
call it a second war of independence. So
remember that animosity between the US
and Great Britain had been growing ever
since the ink was dry on the dang Treaty
of Paris. That's because, as I mentioned
earlier, Great Britain refused to
evacuate troops from its Western forts
in what was now US territory. And more
than that, the British continued to sell
arms to American Indian groups to help
them resist American westward expansion.
And don't forget about the increasing
tension on account of Mak's bill number
two that France used to punish Great
Britain economically. But the last straw
for the US was the continued British
practice of impressment. Basically, in
order to keep up with the demand for
sailors on their Navy ships, whenever
Great Britain seized an American
merchant ship, they forced the Americans
on board to serve in the Royal Navy. So,
not only was this an egregious violation
of US neutrality regarding the
Napoleonic Wars, it was a national
insult to Americans who had fought to be
free of British rule. So, it was about
that time that a debate rose among
American leaders about the prospect of
declaring war on Great Britain. Now,
supporters of the war, known as
Warhawks, argued that Great Britain
would be too distracted by their
conflict with France to pose much of a
threat. and if the US won that would end
Britain's threats to US neutrality while
bonus also proving the US to be a major
player on the world stage. But on the
other side of the debate were mostly
industrial New England federalists who
wanted a renewal of trade with Great
Britain which would improve their own
economic lot drastically and therefore
they staunchly opposed the war. Now in
the end despite massive military
disadvantages the US declared war on
Great Britain. It lasted a little more
than two years and ultimately it ended
in something of a stalemate. The
Americans had some success in driving
the British back into Canada, but for
the most part, the war was a tossup. But
by 1814, Great Britain could no longer
justify the cost of the war, and the two
nations signed the Treaty of Gent, in
which both sides agreed to give up the
lands taken in the war and revert back
to the territorial arrangement present
in 1812. So, to be clear, the war did
not result in any territorial gains for
the United States, but its main effect
was to boost the standing of the US in
the eyes of the world. Like, this was
now the second time the young United
States had defeated Great Britain, the
world's foremost superpower. I mean, to
be fair to say they defeated Britain is
a stretch because it was more like they
just didn't lose. But, you know, we'll
take it. And so, with a new set of
global power pants, the US took it one
step further a few years later by
issuing the Monroe Doctrine. Now, for
context, James Monroe was elected in
1816. And under his leadership, the US
gained metric buttloads of new
territory. For example, Monroe Secretary
of State, John Quincy Adams, negotiated
treaties that established the US Canada
border at the 49th parallel and agreed
to joint US British occupation of the
Oregon territory. Then in 1819, Adams
negotiated the Adams Onus treaty in
which Spain agreed to seed Florida to
the United States. And at the very same
time, several Latin American countries
were revoling and throwing off their
European imperial overlord. And so that
combined with Monroe's success in
shoring up the growing US territory at
the expense of European powers provided
the opportunity to announce the Monroe
Doctrine. It basically announced to the
world that the Western Hemisphere was a
US sphere of influence and that any
further European colonization or
intrusion was unwelcome and would be
resistant. On the flip side, the US
promised not to meddle in European
affairs. Regardless, it was kind of like
America lifted its leg and urinated all
over the Western Hemisphere, much like a
dog might pee on a mailbox in order to
claim it. Wa! Put that leg down, son. As
you can smell, this here hemisphere
belongs to the United States. And for
better or worse, these developments
ultimately led the United States to take
a more significant place of power on the
world stage. Okay, you can click here to
watch my other unit 4 videos, or you can
click here to grab my video note guides,
which are going to help you cram all the
contents of this course firmly into your
brain folds. I'm glad you came around,
and I'll catch you on the flip-flop. I'm
La.